The Sao Paolo Forum was opposed to the free-trade treaties that the USA tried to impose on Latin America.
The Plan B Summit is the european equivalent of the Sao Paolo Forum.
Ladies and gentlemen, the participants of the Sao Paolo Forum were looked down on at the time
and sneered at haughtily.
Well in that forum were those who would later become the members of ten governments in Latin America,
just as the members of ten future european governments are in that room right now.
Fortunately, the only missing members of our summit are precisely those who are on the verge of forming a government.
This is a symbol of the age we are living in.
The greatest hopes are within our reach while the greatest threats are emerging.
We the people of Europe are united, maybe more than other peoples anywhere in the world.
We are united because we went through a period, I would even say two periods, the two World Wars,
when capitalism collapsed because of its own contradictions,
not because the peoples wanted it.
I constantly wear the red triangle, not only because it's the color of my hopes,
but it is also the colour of the symbol that the political deportees wore under the Nazi occupation.
We more than any other know the price to pay when we lose.
United by the past, we are also bound by the present everyday, because we look at each other.
And when elections take place in a country, we look at the result of the party whose ideas are closest to our own.
We don't need to organize meetings to know which party we prefer.
We know this because we inform ourselves and because we follow the development
of the reorganization of the european peoples,
and we're all frightened that the far right is rising.
There is no excuse for this. We know what is happening and where the phenomenon comes from.
It comes from the fact that the right is becoming more radical.
There has always been a popular right, and it is turning into the far right
under the direction of a division of financial capital that benefits from this situation
because its opponents are not the damage of the crisis. We are.
We represent a social and political alternative, a social alternative in particular.
We are the only alternative to the global plundering capitalism is carrying out.
We are also bound by the future.
We know that we are closely interdependent in coping with the threat to the peoples of Europe
that the use of nuclear power in a lot of countries represents,
particularly in a country that is carrying out a war like Ukraine,
where seven of the oldest nuclear power plants in the world stand, like the sarcophagus of Tchernobyl.
We know that we are all confronted with a process of self-collapsing of the organized institution
that we call the European Union and its treaties.
The Brexit is the first indication of this self-collapsing process as is Donald Trump's election on a global scale.
The other indication of this process is of course the rise of the far right.
If the far right is a threat to democracy and social democracy
we must keep in mind that the first threat to democracy is the EU.
It is the EU that bullied Cyprus, Greece and Ireland,
it is the EU that threatens to bully Spain, Portugal, and even my country.
Therefore, our task today is to put an end to this threat to freedom.
We are not just comparing abstract, noble ideas in a scholarly conference
we are acting against a real threat to our civilization's most essential social and democratic benefits.
In 2017 and 2018, it is not through the outcome of a conference, nor even through one of us's wickedness
that problems will emerge. These problems will emerge because they are bound to emerge.
By the year 2017, all the european peoples must know whether they want the TAFTA treaty or not,
or the TTIP... The name of this treaty with the USA changes every year.
Or the CETA treaty with Canada.
In 2017, we must decide what to do with these treaties, otherwise they will decide!
'They' being the rich and powerful; and Juncker, the head of the hooligans,
who was the organizor of the fiscal plundering of all the european countries for many years;
or Angela Merkel, the boss of the european capitalist economy, who accumulated a lot of surplus every year,
which should lead her to be punished more severley than Greece was
because she accumulated this surplus at the expense of all the european countries.
We are going to face this geopolitical reality.
I would like to emphasize what I just said: in 2017 the five european presidents
decided that a new treaty would apply to Europe.
I hope you are all aware that this decision was taken in the month of June 2015
and if you are aware of this, help me inform François Hollande about this.
When I met him after the Brexit, he asked my opinion on this matter.
I first told him that Great-Britain should not be punished for this, and I added that
the new treaty should absolutely stop devastating Europe on a social, monetary and fiscal level.
He said: "What treaty?".
I answered "The new treaty that was decided upon in 2015 and that will be implemented in 2017".
Do you know what he said then?
"No one told us about that" was his answer, although this treaty will be implemented.
The peoples of Europe must become aware that this work has begun and that an official report will be published.
Consequently, the Plan B Summit will be useful to us, in Paris, Rome or Copenhagen.
It will enable us to join our forces in order to face the upcoming events.
There is also another upcoming event no one seems to be willing to talk about.
Do you know what is their response to the dismantling of the world and to Brexit,
and what is their idea for punishing the people of Europe?
Do you think they want to build an atmosphere of enthusiasm by creating new social benefits?
Do they finally want to put an end to the articles of the european treaties that forbid tax harmonization
and that organize the unfair competition between the workers of our countries? No they don't!
Their response is the Europe of Defence! This is the idea they came up with!
We would jump for joy in joining or forces to invade other countries somewhere in the world!
It is on this idea that they wanted to start building Europe in 1954.
No one should forget this! Previous to the Treaty of Rome, the first attempt to build the EU
was the project of a European Defence Community.
The idea was to prepare Europe to resist against or to attack USSR,
and today, they are laying the foundations for the Europe of Defence project.
Let me tell you that if I became the President of France, France will not participate in the Europe of Defence project,
and we will leave NATO's integrated command structure!
We will refuse the logic of a european defence structure because this logic leads to war.
We'd rather that every country be able to defend itself and cooperate with other countries
rather than a new war power emerge, because we know that if it has weapons, it will use them.
History showed that those who arm themselves always use their weapons.
Arming oneself has never led to peace, it has always led to war.
We are in favour of a policy of deterrence.
Dear friends, for now we are developing the idea of a Plan B, but we can't afford to have only one.
We want to develop several Plan Bs, technical and of course political solutions. Why?
Because we must prepare to govern our countries.
Governing is our future, because we believe that the revolution that will sweep over Europe will be a democratic revolution.
Here is what I want to say.
Either we try to cooperate in order to change the EU,
this is our Plan A, which consists in stopping free trade,
in developing cooperative protectionism, in enabling social and fiscal harmonization in Europe...
Either we try to change Europe together
or those of us who refuse the clash of civilizations organized by the EU will have to leave it together.
This is what I hope as I am speaking to you
In a few months, my country will make a choice that cannot be predicted.
The polls say that I am in the lead of all the leftwing political organizations.
I know that I carry a great responsibility on my shoulders,
but I'd like to add that this responsibility is not only on my shoulders, but also on yours,
because if I am elected next year, I'll call for your help and I know you'll be there.